Hello and welcome back to another video
with ItsDrdan and what we are going to be
looking at today is periodic table trends.
So, one thing about our periodic table,
we're, in this video, we are going to
be learning exactly how it came about,
why does it have the shape that it has
today, and what kind of properties can
you actually predict by knowing the
trends of how this thing is organized.
There are a lot of little hidden tools
that are found within it that can
really help build your understanding
of chemistry to help you be able to
do very, very well in your course.
So in this particular video, we're
going to be looking at not only how is
it organized, but how we can actually
see how there are different trends in
here based on the direction of the table
that you're kind of moving towards.
So whether you're going from maybe,
let's say, left to right or from up to
down, up and down, you're going to be
seeing different properties changing.
Um, the ones that we're going to be
really looking at today specifically are
atomic radius, which is how big or small.
These different atoms can actually be,
and keep in mind, we're still talking
atomic scale, so very, very tiny.
Uh, we're also going to be looking
at the ionization energy as well,
which is how easy is it for an atom
to, let's say, lose an electron.
or electron affinity for how
easy is it for it to actually
gain an electron, right?
Those trends go in the same direction.
Um, now there's also a metallic character.
So how metallic is something?
So the more, more like a metal it is,
um, you can see that trend as well.
Um, so we're going to be looking at those
as we kind of move through this and I'll
be explaining all these little details.
So let's try to take a look and
learn and take a bunch of good notes.
And I hope that this video helps you
understand all the different trends that
you will find for your periodic table.
All right.
So one thing that we've realized
through the course of many videos and
all this different chemistry stuff is
that the periodic table, the way that
it's really been shown is it shows
the atomic number, the atomic mass.
And the symbol for all these different
elements that make up the matter
of our world and the universe.
So, at least what's
been discovered so far.
Now, how did it exactly get to the shape?
How are we actually
able to see what it is?
How are there trends behind it?
What does that mean?
So, one thing about it is you
might have noticed is that it's
organized via atomic number.
Which is that, as you see, it goes from 4,
and so forth across your periodic table.
And even if you look at a modern
example, you will see that increase.
Now, that's something that did not just
come from just pure out of nowhere.
There were many scientists that
came and tried to develop all kinds
of versions of the periodic table.
But the one that we really use
today comes from Dmitri Mendeleev.
We really notice that there were
patterns in the periodic table.
Now where exactly do
those patterns come from?
Well, that has to do from the
properties of these different elements.
One thing about the things that have
been observed is that there were matching
properties that were seen, right?
So if we kind of see here, and I.
map out the properties of like,
let's say helium, neon, and argon.
Notice how I've put them on blue.
These are all your noble gases.
They all have very similar properties
being all gases, lithium, sodium,
and then the next element would also
all have very reactive tendencies.
Whereas beryllium and magnesium
tend to be a little bit more stable.
They're similar to one another.
So the chemical properties of these
different elements were similar.
Now, As a result of this being when they
were able to line up all the different
elements, they were able, he was able
to see that, oh, what if I try to
move this in a different way, we can
actually see that things are starting
to line up with one another, that these
elements actually have, if we increase
them by the atomic number, which is
the protons of these things, that we're
actually able to determine Uh, what
is, what are the different properties?
Now, originally, this was done by mass,
originally, being that they didn't really
know entirely about protons at the time,
but they were able to line them all up
by their, uh, by their numbers over time
as it was further and further developed.
So, this is how all
this kind of came to be.
We were able to organize the whole
entire periodic table via properties.
So, what can we see in terms of
the major classifications of this?
Um, when we look at the periodic table,
if we kind of organize all the little
parts, the left side of the periodic
table, it happens to now all be metals.
Every single one of these right
from there's a zigzag generally
on all your periodic tables,
you'll see as a bold line.
This denotes on the left side of
it, sorry, left side is all metals.
So these are very good conductors
of heat and electricity.
They can be formed into different objects.
They also lose electrons
very easily as well.
They're either very good cat ions.
On the right hand side of the periodic
table is where all the non-metals are,
meaning that their, their phase can vary.
They can be gases, they can be liquids.
They can be solids.
It's very easy for them to change.
Uh, a lot of these tend to be what
we see in the organic chemistry area.
Um, they also tend to gain electrons as
well, so they have that tendency to gain.
Now in the middle is quite, doesn't
fit on one side or the other.
Other.
This is where we call the metallos.
So metalloids, so it comes right in
the middle of the two, two different
classifications because they, they are
very good as semiconductors, whereas like
non metals couldn't be, you know, semi
couldn't actually conduct electricity.
The metals could, they fall
in the fall in the middle.
So they have a little bit
of properties of both sides.
They don't just fit in one or the other.
So generally this area is the middle.
Um, so we classify these now, this helps
us be able to label and predict what all
these different elements can do, which
is always very, very important, right?
The ability to prediction is kind of what
makes science interesting and lets you
be able to make hypothesis, try to make
scientific theory to determine what can
everything, what can happen now going
even farther when we look at these, right?
Where we have all those
individual classifications.
There's more ways we can
label the periodic table too.
The first thing is on the left and the
right side of the table, where I kind of
call them like the two, maybe like the two
towers of the periodic table, um, we can
label our, as our main group of elements.
So the main group tends to be where
all, where most of the chemistry
and introductory chemistry and
general chemistry one takes place.
We typically like to look
around here cause it's.
It's more easily predictable.
Um, this is where your
predictable ion charges come from.
They have, uh, They don't really
have any sort of crazy chemistry.
This is where a lot of the type
1 ionic compounds are going to be
born out of, which you will see
in future videos or other videos.
Now in the middle, this is
where the transition metals are.
These are where, these ones
are not as predictable.
This is where the chemistry
can get really wild and crazy.
This is what tends to be a lot of
the things that are used within
your, within your cell phones,
as batteries, as conductors of
electricity in all of our devices.
Um, they can really have a, a
lot of different interesting
properties that can be seen.
This is where we refer
to as type 2 metals.
Um, especially when it comes to
cations being used for ionic compounds.
So keep that in mind when it comes to
those classifications and how we can
label all these different species.
Now, we have all these labels, right?
Label, label, label.
We like to be organized and
try to discuss everything.
The other thing that we also have is
what we refer to as groups and periods,
which is how we discuss columns and rows.
Um, it's for, to me, I always think of
groups and periods as a very archaic
dated language going back to the
early 19th, to the mid 19th century.
Generally, I like to refer to them
as columns and rows a lot, but
groups and periods is used across
the entire world and probably
will never go away anytime soon.
So, usually, the way that we label
groups and families, so columns, is there
are two ways that they can be labeled.
Um, depends on the
periodic table you have.
If you count every column across the
periodic table, you will have 18 columns.
However, depending on if you have
an older or newer table, you're
going to see two labeling systems.
They're both useful in their own way.
If you have Roman numerals on top
of the table, Where it's going
from 1 to 8 in Roman numerals,
and it has an A next to it, that's
labeling your main group elements.
And then if it has a 1 through
10 B, that's labeling your,
your transition metals.
Rows are what we use to really
determine energy levels, what we use
for electron configuration, um, how
we can try to organize our periodic
table to really be able to determine
exactly what it is that we have.
All kinds of labels that are here.
All of them are very useful, um,
when we're going through those.
And if you kind of look at some of
these, we can even lay, look even
farther, all the groups that we have,
when it comes to those columns, they
are your families that were covered
in previous videos, and generally at
the very beginning of the semester.
So each of these columns, we can see
the first one is the alkali metals.
All of these are
extremely reactive metals.
They all have the same properties
when you move on to let's say
the alkaline earth metals.
These are different, these are different,
uh, elements that are generally
more stable, but they do have the
characteristic of a lot of the different
colors you see, like in fireworks and
flames and all these kinds of different
potential possibilities to them.
Um, then we have our
nictogens and our chalcogens.
They have their own unique properties,
halogens are very, very reactive, and
then the noble gases are something that is
usually very inert, and they don't react.
So the PUREC table is
organized by those properties.
And we can determine, if I tell
you, okay, let's find a, A molecule
in 16 and period number two, you
could find oxygen in that location.
You can use it as like a way to
index where everything is to be able
to call out where all those are.
It's a way to be able to
label and determine where you
can find different species.
Um, now moving forward, uh, what
other kinds of patterns can we see?
All right, so what patterns do we
actually see in the periodic table?
Let's take a look at it.
So other than trying to classify the
different types of elements, We can
also see that there are other trends.
So one of the things that we
learned in previous videos is
what ions do alkali metals make?
And one thing you realize is that all of
that entire column were plus one, right?
Column one were all plus one.
Now if I ask you, okay,
what about halogens?
Well, they also had a predictable charge.
If you remember that entire
column was negative one behind
all those individual charges.
You could predict and assign all those.
Now when it comes to all of these,
they all have a trend that comes with
the electron configurations as well.
Um, we followed a very, very specific
pattern, meaning that There is a
pattern for atoms to be able to
gain and lose valence electrons.
The entire idea about the main
group of elements was that they
want to achieve the octet rule.
The goal was to get to 8
electrons no matter what.
So one of the things that we could see is
that predictable ions have essentially a
predictable number of valence electrons.
Meaning we could see how many Uh, how
many, uh, electrons we want to be able to
lose or gain in order to get to all those
individual, to get that octet role, right?
If we look at column one, right,
it has one valence electron.
Well, what is the charge of column one?
If you remember, it's plus one.
meaning that it has the urge to
want to lose that one electron.
Now, if you go to the next column,
you'll see those two valence electrons.
Well, what was the charge
of that column as well?
It was two plus meaning that it wants
to lose those two electrons to help it
achieve that octet rule to have a complete
and filled valence electron shell.
If you move across, you'll see that,
oh, we'll go to 3 and then, uh, then
eventually to 3 So on the 3 right,
there's three valence electrons, so if
we lose all three, he'll get an octet.
If we go to, uh, where it has five
valence electrons, Well, all it
needs is 3 to get to 8, right?
So 8 minus 5 is 3.
So gain 3, we can get 8.
And we can see that pattern can
grow as you kind of get closer
and closer to 8 electrons.
So there was a pattern based
on the predictable charges.
which is related to the amount of
valence electrons that we have within
the molecule, which is actually
kind of cool when you see it, right?
There are trends all around us.
Now, what do ions have in common when,
when we're gaining and losing electrons?
There's something else
that gets affected as well.
So when it comes to having the tendency
to make a plus charge, or a negative
charge, this is something that will
affect the atomic size, meaning how big
or small are these different elements.
So one thing is that we're going to see
is as you go from across the periodic
table from right to left, we're going to
see that the size is going to increase.
Now why does it have that tendency?
So when you go first, let's start by going
down the periodic table because that's
usually the easiest way to see it first.
I should have started there.
If you remember from electron
configuration, the first, the very top
left of the periodic table was 1s1,
right, right where hydrogen is, it has
that one in front of the entire number.
Now, if I go down that periodic
table and I go down to lithium, which
is 1s2, 2s1, the orbital is going
to get bigger when it gets to two.
Now if I continue to go down, that
orbital is going to grow again to
three and it's going to get bigger
and bigger and bigger as you travel
down the size of the periodic table.
So one thing that we can see is that the
orbital is getting larger, meaning that
it's the size is increasing as we go down.
Now what about as you go across?
Well, if I go from, uh, going
from, uh, if I look at, let's
say, carbon versus nitrogen versus
oxygen, well, what can we see?
What are the exact differences?
Well, let's first start with, uh, the
very first one, which is looking at,
um, looking at carbon here, which has
six protons, versus nitrogen, which
has seven, and oxygen, which has eight.
Now, one thing that you're kind of looking
at here is we're looking at p orbitals.
And we can see that they're getting more.
They're getting smushed.
They're getting a little bit closer
and getting a little bit closer as
we go from left to right, meaning
that they're getting smaller, right?
So as you go to the right hand side of
the periodic table, they get tinier.
Why is that?
Well, it's because you have so many
protons that are attracting all the
electrons closer and closer and closer
to the center of the atom as a result.
So you're going to see that there is this
trend where atomic radius is going to get
bigger as you go from, go from the top
right all the way down to the bottom left.
it's going to get larger.
So we have a trend that is here.
So if I asked you like the following
question as an example, and I said,
okay, let's try to rank all the different
atoms in their sizes that we have here.
So I have gallium, phosphorus, sulfur, and
you rank them from smallest to largest.
Now, if you remember our trend,
right, the top right of the
periodic table are the smallest.
So that means sulfur would be
first, phosphorus would be second,
then gallium would be the largest
out of them as we move across.
And this is because the farther you're
going down into the left, the one
that are the highest quantum number
is getting bigger, bigger, bigger.
And there's only one, maybe one valence
electron, maybe two valence electrons
that are on the outermost level.
So they're not really feeling the
attraction as much as other species.
Um, so this is the idea that
we look at when we're looking
at neutral atomic radii.
Now, what about ionic radii?
Well, atomic, if you
remember, was neutral species.
But what happens to an ion?
How does the, how does the size
change if you're changing how
positive or negative something is?
Well, the one way for us to look at it
is, let's say if we want to have a cation.
What exactly would happen?
Well, remember the, uh, this is all about
the number of electrons is changing.
So let's say if I take away
one electron from you, what
exactly are you going to do?
Or heck, even better yet, think about
it in terms of how, let's say if you
had 5 and that's all you had to your
name and I take 1, meaning I took 20
percent of your money that you have.
What would you do immediately?
That's when we start getting cheaper,
we don't want to spend any of our
money, when we start seeing that
our bank account's a little low
and we don't really have that much.
So you're going to try to hoard and
bring all those closer, because you don't
want to lose any of them as a result.
So when we lose one electron, the force
of attraction between all the protons
is going to increase, because remember,
electrons, they push each other away.
But they're not going to be,
it's not going to be felt as much
because now that it's not even
anymore, there's more protons.
So they're going to come
closer and closer together.
Now with anions, it's
going to be the opposite.
They're going to get bigger when we
put more electrons and that's because
they're all pushing each other away.
Their personal space bubble
is going to be too felt.
It's kind of like once you get your
paycheck for the week and all of a sudden
you're like, Oh, I'm going to buy this.
I'm going to buy that.
I'm going to buy this.
Like you're kind of going to be a little
bit frivolous, a little less caring.
It's you're not going to hold
your money as close to yourself.
We want to continue that example.
Um, so the more you have, the more
repulsion is going to get bigger.
So anions are larger at ions are smaller.
So to show the size
difference between those.
I have a neutral atom has zero in the
middle here in gray, pink is anion,
and then the light blue is a cation.
And you can see that the size
difference, and if I want to increase
the charge, let's say if I want
to make it more and more positive,
me, I'm taking more electrons away.
It's going to keep getting smaller
and smaller because the nucleus
is now overwhelmingly positive.
It doesn't really want to potentially
lose any more electrons either.
So it's also going to hold
everything very close.
Versus an anion, it's going
to get larger and larger.
and larger as a result.
So we can really see that there is a
very big difference when it comes to the
sizes of all these different species.
Okay.
So when we're trying to look at all
these different trends, we can see
that as we move from, as we go down
the periodic table, The size is gonna
get bigger, and as we move from the
right hand side to the left hand
side, it's gonna get bigger as well.
So it's gonna be going kind of
in a diagonal from right to left.
And then cat ions are
small and ions are big.
Um, what other trend that we have?
So there's one other one.
There's one other major one
that we're gonna look at.
And it has to do with essentially
looking at ionization energy.
Now break down that word,
the first three letters, ion.
So it has to do something with ions.
Now ionization energy is how easy is it
for a neutral atom to lose an electron?
How is it easy to be removed?
Um, they're depending on your course.
So in introductory chemistry, we
only worry about this, but if you're
taking general chemistry, you might
also have to worry about electron
affinity, which is the opposite.
It's all about, uh, how attracted are
you to an electron, but the trends
still go in the same direction.
So if we're going to lose an
electron, this is something where.
Well, it's going to be easier in
certain directions over another.
So how exactly can we see that?
Well, in terms of patterns, it's all
about, well, where's the positive energy?
Where is the negative energy?
When you travel towards the negative
side of the periodic table, so
closer to fluorine in the top right.
The energy to remove an electron is going
to be higher because it does not want to
lose an electron, it wants to gain one.
So it's going to get really, really
hard to pull off an electron when
you have a negative one charge.
It only needs that one
electron to get a negative one.
So the energy increases as
you go up and to the right.
Um, essentially, the more, the farther
and farther the electron gets away
from the nucleus, the more valence
it becomes, it becomes a lot easier.
So as you travel downwards,
you can see the energy would be
really, really low as a result.
Um, as you're trying to travel
through, trying to look across
all these different trends.
Um, now when we're, so let's go
through and try to summarize all
these and go to back to our original.
All right.
So we're going to summarize
everything we talked about to
going back to the beginning.
All the trends, so as we go from up
into the right of the Piroc table.
So going in this direction,
towards fluorine, we will see
the ionization energy increases.
Meaning it takes a lot of work
to remove those electrons.
All of these guys, if you remember, were
all negative 1, negative 2, negative 3.
They're stuff that do not want to lose
them, so that's why it's so much higher.
It takes work, right?
Energy is something that takes effort.
How easy is it for you to go to the
gym, or to run, or do all these things?
It takes a lot of work.
The radius is how big it's going to get.
Now notice how the trends are
opposite of each other, meaning the
bigger that the molecule is, the
easier it is to rip an electron off.
So if it's very, very large and has
a lot of electrons, as we get down
to the bottom to the left, right, if
you think of fran, franzium, which is
right here at the bottom, it has 87
electrons, so, and there's only one in
the outermost layer, so it's going to be
really easy to misplace it, or lose it.
So being that so far away now, the
other trend they did not really
necessarily talk about, but is
metallic character that has to do with
the characterization of the table.
Remember, the left were all metals,
the rights, all non metals will, as
you go more farther away from the non
metals, the more metallic things become.
Okay.
So all these are more
metallic than the non metals.
Okay, so this is the general idea.
It's a lot of info.
Hopefully, you can kind of get a
basic idea that there's a lot of
things buried in your PR table.
Um, tons of information, tons to learn.
Thank you so much for listening.
I hope this video helped a
little bit, and I look forward
to seeing you all in the future.
I'll see you all later.
Bye now.